Guide to the Alma Lutz Papers, 1906-1973
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
- Series II. Historical Biography Material
  - Shaw, Anna Howard, (Copies) (Box 18)
  - Shaw, Anna Howard (Box 18)
  - Shaw, Anna Howard — Photographs (Box 18)
  - Sigourney, Lydia Huntley, (Copies from the Alma Lutz Collection) (Box 18)
  - Sigourney, Lydia H. — 1791-1865 (Box 18)
  - Smith, Elizabeth Oakes (Box 18)
  - Smith, Elizabeth Oakes (Box 18)
  - Smith, Gerrit (Box 18)
  - Smith, Gerrit — to Susan B. Anthony (Box 18)
  - Smith, Julia (Box 18)
  - Smith, Julia — 1792-1886 (Box 18)
  - Somerville, Mary (Box 18)
  - Spencer, Mary E. (Box 18)
  - Stanton, Elizabeth Cady and Others — Letters — Duplicates in File (Box 18)
  - Stanton, Elizabeth Cady — Letters to Clara B. Colbys, (copies) (Box 18)
  - Stanton, Elizabeth Cady — Sayings (Box 18)
  - Stanton, Elizabeth Cady — Letters to Gerrit Smith, (Copies) (Box 18)
  - Stanton, Elizabeth Cady, (Copies from the Alma Lutz Collection) (Box 18)
  - Stanton, Elizabeth Cady — Miscellaneous, (Copies) (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Family (Box 18)
  - Stanton, Henry Brewster — 1805-1887 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Childhood (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Youth, School Days (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Marriage (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.c. — Europe, 1840 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1841-1842 — Johnstown, Motherhood (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1843-1846 — Boston (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1847-1849 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1848 — Convention (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1850 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1851 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1852 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Peterboro (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Seneca Falls (1847-1862) General (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Bloomer Costume (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — The Lily (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1853 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1854 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1855 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1856 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1857 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1858 — 59 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1860 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Outlines (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Correspondence re: material for Lutz biography (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Library references for Lutz biography (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — as Grandmother (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Articles about (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Indexes for Lutz biography (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Sources for Lutz biography (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Photographs (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Ida Husted Harper (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Description of Characteristics (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Comments on Life of (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Suffrage Organizations (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Magazine Articles (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Amendments (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Marriage and Divorce (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Miscellaneous undated material (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Look up (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1863-1864 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1861-1862 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1865 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1866 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1867-1868 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Kansas, 1867 (Box 18)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1869 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — The Revolution — 1868-1870 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Lecture Tours (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1870 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1871 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1872 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1873 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1874-1879 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1880-1889 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1880-1883 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1884-1886 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1887-1889 — Europe (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1890-1891 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1892-1894 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1890-1895 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1895 — Birthday Celebration (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1896 — Woman's Bible, Religion (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1897-1898 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1899 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1898 — Eighty Years and More: 1815-1897 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1900 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — 1901-1802 (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Photographs (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Publications (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Quotations (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Leaflets (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Play (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Lutz Corrections for Created Equal — Letters (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Birthday — Clippings (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — Clippings (Box 19)
  - Stanton, E.C. — On Labor — Socialism — Copy (Box 19)
  - Stanton, Robert and Theodore — Letters, (Copies) (Box 19)
  - Stanton, Henry B. (Box 19)
  - Stevens, Doris (Box 19)
  - Stone, Lucy — Letters (Box 19)
  - Stone, Lucy — Letters, (Copies from the Alma Lutz Collection) (Box 19)
  - Stone, Lucy (Box 19)
  - Stone, Lucy — Photographs (Box 19)
  - Stowe, Harriet Beecher (Box 19)
  - Swisshelm, Jane Gray (Box 19)
  - Thayer, Julia H. (Box 19)
  - Thomas, M. Carey (Box 19)
  - Train, George Francis (Box 19)
  - Tubman, Harriet (Box 19)
  - Upton, Harriet Taylor (Box 19)
  - Van Walters, Dr. Miriam (Box 19)
  - Vernon, Mabel (Box 19)
  - Voorhis, John Van, (Copies) (Box 19)
  - Walker, Dr. Mary, (Copies) (Box 19)
  - Walton, Major J. M. (Box 19)
  - Warren, Mery — Letter to, (Original) (Box 19)
  - Warren, Mercy (Box 19)
  - Wheatley, Phillis (Box 19)
  - Whittier (Box 19)
  - Widdemer, Margaret (Box 19)
  - Willard, Emma, (Copies from the Alma Lutz Collection) (Box 19)
  - Willard, Emma (Box 19)
  - Willard, Emma — Photographs (Box 19)
  - Willard, Emma — Ancestry — Capt. Samuel Hart — Lydia Hinsdale Hart (Box 19)
  - Willard, Emma — Connecticut: Farmington, Berlin — Social Life and Customs (Box 19)
  - Willard, Emma — Girlhood and Early Education (Box 19)
  - Willard, Emma — Education 1800 (Box 19)
  - Willard, Emma — Teaching and Studying (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — The Plan (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Middlebury, VT (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Waterford (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Founding of Troy Female Seminary (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Efforts for Greece (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Educational Ideas (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Lafayette's Visit (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Troy Female Seminary (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Troy Female Seminary, 1830 — 38 (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — European Trip, 1830 (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Work for Common School in CT (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — General Work for Education (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Histories (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Normal School Idea (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Second Marriage and Divorce (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Troy, 1838-1844 (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — 1844-1870 (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Women's Rights (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Last Years (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Bibliography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Correspondence re: material for Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Chronology for Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Photographs for Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Character (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Pupils (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Emma Willard Association (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Other Writings (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Contemporary Schools (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Geography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Corrections for Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Outlines for Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Sources for Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — First Draft for Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — New Material for Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Contemporaries (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Lutz Correspondence with Publishers (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Lutz Correspondence with Houghton Mifflin (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Reviews of Lutz Biography and Letters (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Advertising and Marketing of Lutz Biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Copies of Lutz Biography sent to (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — 1964 Lutz Biography Reviews (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Reviews and Material for 1964 Lutz Biography Jacket (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Letters re (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Clippings (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Historical References Clippings (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Speeches (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Acknowledgements, Chronology, Index for Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Correspondence re: new edition of Lutz biography (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Lutz Beacon Press Correspondence (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Emma Willard Publications (Box 20)
  - Willard, Emma — Emma Willard Fund (Box 20)
  - Willard, Frances E. (Box 20)
  - Willard, Frances E., (Copies from the Alma Lutz Collection) (Box 20)
  - Wollstonecraft, Mary, (Copies from the Alma Lutz Collection) (Box 20)
  - Woodhull, Victoria (Box 20)
  - Woodhull, Victoria (Box 20)
  - Woolley, Mary E. (Box 20)
  - Wright, Frances (Box 20)
  - Wright, Frances (Box 20)
  - Wright, Martha C. (Box 20)
  - Wright, Martha C., (Copies) (Box 20)
  - Zenger, Anna (Box 20)
- Series III. Miscellaneous
  - Biographical information about Alma Lutz; photographs of herself, family, and friends; family letters; miscellaneous correspondence, 1971, and correspondence relating to her articles; and materials relating to the Vassar Centennial, Class of 1912, and Vassar-Yale study. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and information relating to Schlesinger Library (Lutz was a member of the Advisory Board from 1961 until her death); the Sophia Smith Collection; correspondence with Vassar College Library about materials on women; and information on other women's history collections, bibliographies, etc. (Folders 2.1-2.25)
  - Women's history courses (Folder 2.26)
  - Lucy Stone League (Folder 2.27)
  - Margaret Brent Fellowship (Folder 2.28)
  - U.S. President's Commission on the Status of Women (Folders 2.29-2.35)
  - The National Woman's Party and the Equal Rights Amendment. Includes information; correspondence (Alice Paul, Emma Guffey Miller); manuscripts of articles and speeches; clippings; information about 1945-47 Party controversy; endorsements by men; opposition to ERA; American Association of University Women and ERA; and Massachusetts Branch of the National Woman's Party and Massachusetts Committee for ERA. (Box 3)
  - World Woman's Party, International Labor Office, and United Nations (Folders 4.1-4.3)
  - Seneca Falls Woman's Rights Convention, 1848 (Folders 4.4-4.12)
  - First National Woman's Rights Convention, Boston, 1850, and Boston Convention, 1859. (Folders 4.13-4.14)
  - Women suffrage. Includes history, documents, publications, songs, posters, Wyoming, New York, England, anti-suffrage publications, and Alma Lutz manuscripts (Folders 4.15-4.35)
  - Women's history. Includes colonial women, western pioneer women, women and labor (Lowell Mill girls), early women printers, lawyers and business women, dress reform, and English women. (Folders 5.1-5.26)
  - Antislavery movement. Includes bibliography, publications, correspondence, notes, material on women's role and female antislavery (Folders 5.27-5.53)
  - Bibliographies of various library collections on women (Boxes 21-22)
  - Reports of Radcliffe's Schlesinger Library (Box 23)
  - Reports and publications of Smith College Library, Sophia Smith Collection, (1 box and 1 envelope) (Box 24)
  - The Open Door International (for the economic emancipation of the woman worker), 1929-1970 (Boxes 25-26)
  - Other international women's organizations (Box 27)
  - UN bulletins and other materials on status of women and human rights, 1946-1958 (Boxes 28-30)
  - UN Commission on the Status of Women, 1947-1970 (Box 31)
  - Inter-American Commission of Women, 1938-1963. Includes a folder of clippings, correspondence, and statements. (Box 32)
  - Pamphlets and clippings on women in various countries, 1 box (Box 33)
  - Legal status of women in the U.S. (Mostly publications of Women's Bureau, 1930-, and President's Commission on the Status of Women) (Boxes 34-35)
  - Women's Bureau publications on wage and hour legislation and surveys by occupation and geographical areas (Boxes 36-38)
  - Other pamphlets on women workers (Box 39)
  - Material on the Equal Rights Amendment, 1924-1973 (Boxes 40-44)
  - Women in World War II and in the armed forces (Boxes 45-46)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets on women, women in law, women in the church (Box 47)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets relating to education of women (Box 48)
  - Women's Liberation (Box 49)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets relating to American history (Box 50)
  - Photostats of material relating to Susan B. Anthony, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Margaret Elizabeth Chandler, Laura Clay, Abby Kelley Foster, Benjamin Lundy, and antislavery women. (Boxes 51-52)
  - Index cards (Boxes 53-59)
  - Copies of books written by or edited by Alma Lutz, including copies of Created Equal and Challenging Years, with marginal notes by Lutz; 2 books used by A.L. at Vassar; a copy of Mary Beard's WOMAN AS FORCE IN HISTORY (1946), marked by A.L.; and copies of the papers presented at seminars on American Women at Radcliffe, 1951/52 and 1952/53. (Box 60)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets and articles (Box 61)
  - Miscellaneous oversized pamphlets and articles (Box 62)